<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A protestation of the most high and mighty Prince Charles Lodowicke, Count Palatine of the Rhine, archidapifer, and prince elector of the sacred empire, Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c. translated out of the High-Dutch ...</title>
            <title>Protestatio serenissimi &amp; celsissimi principis Caroli Ludovici. English</title>
            <author>Karl Ludwig, Elector Palatine, 1617-1680.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 12 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18500</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5050</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107767</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">22216304</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 22216304</idno>
            <idno type="VID">25234</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18500)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 25234)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1229:27 or 1748:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A protestation of the most high and mighty Prince Charles Lodowicke, Count Palatine of the Rhine, archidapifer, and prince elector of the sacred empire, Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c. translated out of the High-Dutch ...</title>
                  <title>Protestatio serenissimi &amp; celsissimi principis Caroli Ludovici. English</title>
                  <author>Karl Ludwig, Elector Palatine, 1617-1680.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 26 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>For Richard Whitaker,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Printed at London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M. DC. XXXVII [1637]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Protestatio serenissimi &amp; celsissimi principis Caroli Ludovici.</note>
                  <note>"Given at Hampton-court, the 27. of January, anno 1637"--Colophon.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴ (last leaf blank).</note>
                  <note>Reproductions of originals in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art (reel 1229) and Harvard University. Library (1748).</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Palatinate (Germany) --  History.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>Judith Siefring</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:1"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 1 -->
            <p>A PROTESTATION Of the Moſt High and Mighty PRINCE <hi>CHARLES
LODOWICKE,</hi> Count Palatine of the Rhine, Archidapifer, and Prince Elector
of the ſacred Empire, Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c.</p>
            <figure/>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the High-Dutch, and Printed at LONDON for
RICHARD WHITAKER, M.DC.XXXVII.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="argument">
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:2"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 2 -->
            <p>THE </p>
            <p>PROTESTATION</p>
            <p> Is againſt</p>
            <p> All the unlawfull, and violent proceedings and actions,
intended and practiſed to his Highneſſe, his Brethren, and neare Kindreds
prejudice.</p>
            <p>Particularly, againſt</p>
            <p> The ſecret, and invalide diſpoſitions and decrees of the
Emperour, in the tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlation of the Electorall dignity and domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions, upon
the Duke of Bavaria, &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Secondly,</p>
            <p> The unlawfull, and vaine Election of a King of the Romans,
where his Highneſſe and the Electour of Triers were excluded.</p>
            <p>Laſtly,</p>
            <p> The violent and unjuſt uſurpation and poſſeſſion of
the Electorall Dignity, Title, Voice, and Seſſion, by the Duke of
Bavaria.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="epigraphs">
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <q> 
               <p>A Proteſtation, eſpecially being cleare and well
expreſſed, conſerveth the right of him that maketh it. And though ſuch
proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on be neceſſary, yet doth it no wrong, or injury to any one.</p>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Leg.<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>idebitor</hi> 4. § 1. <hi>D. Quibus modis pignus &amp;
ibi Bartol. l. &amp; ſi quis,</hi> 14 §. <hi>Sed interdum</hi> 7. <hi>D.
de Religioſe. &amp; ſumptibus.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>Sampſon, when the Philiſtins, tooke his wife from him,
and gave her to another, maketh this Proteſtation againſt them.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Iudges cap.</hi> 15. <hi>verſ.</hi> 3.</bibl> 
               <p>Now ſhall I be more blameleſſe than the Philiſtins,
though I doe them a diſpleaſure.</p>
            </q>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:25234:3"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 3 -->
            <opener>
               <signed>Charles Lodowicke, By the grace of God, Count Palatine of the
Rhine, Archidapifer, and Prince Electour of the ſacred Empire, Duke of
Bavaria, &amp;c.</signed>
               <salute>To all, and every one, that ſhall ſee or reade
theſe our Letters Patents, Greeting.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>T is well knowne and manifeſt, not onely in the Roman
Empire, and Germany our <pb n="2" facs="tcp:25234:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->deare
Country, but alſo in all Chriſtendome, by the experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence of thoſe
violent actions and ſad effects of warre, which even unto this day are to bee
ſeene, and by divers writings and publique monuments ſet forth every where,
what man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of proceeding was uſed, all the while theſe heauy trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles,
and civill warres of Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manie laſted, in the occupation, ſurreption,
diviſion, diſmem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bring, <pb n="3" facs="tcp:25234:4"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 4 -->ſale,
grant, and tranſlati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Our now waſted Domi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nions and Territories; and
well as of Our Electorall Dignity, Archidapiferſhip, Voice, Royalties, and
other Rights thereunto immediately and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeparably belonging.</p>
            <p>Which proceedings and violences being altogether un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juſt,
intolerable, contrary to all right and juſtice, and conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quently 
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:25234:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->a nullity, invalide, and without
power and force: We have juſt cauſe to be ſenſible of them, and to this
end to pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh Our complaints, excepti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and proteſtations againſt
them, according as neceſsity and juſtice doth require.</p>
            <p>Eſpecially, that which grie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth &amp; moſt ſenſibly
afflicteth Vs, as tending to the greateſt prejudice of Our owne, Our 
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:25234:5"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 5 -->Brethren and neere Kindreds
Perſons and Rights, is that not without great diſlike and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row We doe
heare and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand.</p>
            <p>Firſt of all, how that in the laſt pretended treaty of peace
at Prague, without Our know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in the time of Our mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nority, not being
there, nor ſent for, nor heard, amongſt the reſt was concluded and agreed
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:25234:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->upon, that thoſe
diſpoſitions and pactions ſhould bee and remaine firme, ſtable aad
va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lide, which heretofore were made and granted by his Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Majeſty, to
the Duke of Bavaria, and the Wilhel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mian Line and Poſterity, in regard of Our
Electorall Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minions and Dignities, and withall, that the ſaid invalide
diſpoſgions, having beene parched &amp; compiled together 
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:25234:6"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 6 -->in private and ſecretly,
hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to unknowne to the world, and as yet not publiſhed in their true force
and phraſe, never<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theleſſe were alledged againſt Us, under the
pretence, as if they had beene allowed and confirmed in the ſayd treaty of
peace, and conſequently re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceived by a generall approba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of all the
ſtates of the Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Empire, as it doth mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtly appeare in the laſt
anſwer <pb n="8" facs="tcp:25234:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->given by the Emperour to
the Earle of Arundel, the Kings Majeſty of Great Brittaine His
Ambaſſadour at Ratisbone.</p>
            <p>By vertue of which diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, Our Right, Iuriſdictions
and Poſſeſsions, belonging and appertaining unto Vs, Our Brethren, and
neare Kindred, <hi>ex primaevâ &amp; ſimultaneâ
Inveſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turâ ex pacto &amp; providentiâ majo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> were
raviſhed and vio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lently <pb n="9" facs="tcp:25234:7"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 7 -->taken
from Vs, and transferred from Our Houſe to a remote and farre diſtant Line
and Deſcent, againſt all right, lawes, conſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons of the Empire,
cuſtomes obſerved in Fiefs of ſuch importance and quality; nay, even
againſt the Gol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den Bull it ſelfe, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther pactions and Imperiall
priviledges, from many ages conferred and confirmed up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on 
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:25234:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->on Our Electorall Houſe.</p>
            <p>Secondly, it much grieveth Vs, that at the laſt meeting of the
Electours at Ratisbone, where the election of a King of the Romans was
propoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded and treated, and the King of Hungary, <hi>Ferdinando</hi> of
Auſtria, choſen and crowned, We were not with the reſt of Our
Co-electors, by vertue of the Golden Bull, called and 
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:25234:8"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 8 -->invited, notwithſtanding that
VVe onely repreſent and beare the Right, Voice, Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice, and Perſon of the
Elector Palatine, but VVe were pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſely, though uniuſtly, paſt by and
excluded, and the Duke of Bavaria ſuffered <hi>de facto</hi> and really to
uſurpe, and to beare our Title, Place, Seſſion, Office and Voice,
againſt all Law and Iuſtice.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:25234:9"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->
            <p>All theſe things generally, and every one in particular being
nothing, and altogether invalide, uniuſt, and violent, to paſſe by many
other nulli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, VVe doe eſteeme and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count the Diſpoſitions
above-ſaid, and the pretended con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluſion of peace of no force and power,
upon this ground, becauſe they were continued, framed and agreed upon, in the
time of Our, and Our <pb n="13" facs="tcp:25234:9"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 9 -->Brethrens
minority, when We were abſent and in for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raine Countries, having beene
neither called nor heard, much leſſe accuſed and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>victed; beſides,
that in them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves they are contrary to all Divine and humane lawes, the
fundamentall Conſtitutions of the Sacred Empire, the or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinary cuſtomes of
Fiefs of ſuch quality, and the manifold declarations, which His Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall 
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:25234:10"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->Majeſty hath made and given
under his owne hand with full aſſurance, to all the Electours, that then
were pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent, the 23. of February, <hi>anno</hi> 1623. and to the King of
Great Brittaine, Our honou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red Grandfather of moſt bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed memory, few
daies after, <hi>viz.</hi> the 5. of March in the ſame yeare.</p>
            <p>And withall the nullity of this <pb n="15" facs="tcp:25234:10"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 10 -->pretended
Election appeareth, in that. VVe were with the E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectour of Triers unjuſtly
and violently excluded and kept out from it, though unto Us onely it belongeth
by Nature, Divine and humane lawes, to beare the Name, Title, Voice, Office,
and Function of the Electour Palatine, in all Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periall Diets, Electorall
mee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tings, and generally in all ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lemne actions of the Empire.</p>
            <pb n="16" facs="tcp:25234:11"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->
            <p>Theſe inevitable neceſsities obliged Vs, to publiſh Our
exceptions and proteſtations in a ſolemne and legall man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, for the
maintaining of Our unqueſtionable and un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doubted Right, Iuriſdiction,
Princely deſcent, State, and Name, againſt all ſuch and the like violent
proceedings, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, determined and pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſed, to the prejudice and
diſgrace of Vs, Our Brethren <pb n="17" facs="tcp:25234:11"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 11 -->and
neere Kindred, who were never ſo much as called or heard in Our owne
cauſe.</p>
            <p>We doe therefore by ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tue of theſe Letters Patents, with
good adviſe and know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, in the beſt forme and wiſe, according to Law
and Cuſtome, plainely and fully proteſt againſt, and contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dict all,
both in generall and particular, whatſoever hath been contrived, acted,
granted, <pb n="18" facs="tcp:25234:12"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->premiſed,
pronounced, judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, publiſhed, diſpoſed, practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed and agreed upon,
publike<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly or privately, with delibera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and purpoſe, or any other way, to
the prejudice, detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and damage of Us, Our Brethren, and neare Kindred, or
whatſoever ſhall or may be in time to come, ordained, judged, decreed,
practiſed and acted, againſt Vs, <hi>de facto</hi> and really, without Our
know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, <pb n="19" facs="tcp:25234:12"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 12 -->conſent and
appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bation.</p>
            <p>Particularly, we doe proteſt againſt thoſe vaine,
imperti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent, and moſt dangerous diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, and concluſions of
peace at Prague, againſt the haſty, precipitate and unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full election of
a King of the Romans, and above all, againſt the violent, unjuſt and
hainous uſurpation, detention, and pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vation <pb n="20" facs="tcp:25234:13"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->made
and continued by the Duke of Bavaria, in keeping backe, raviſhing and
detaining from Vs, as much as lyeth in his power, by his uſurpation <hi>de
facto,</hi> Our E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectourſhip, Dominions, Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jects, Royalties, Fiefs,
Office, Title, Voice and Seſsion.</p>
            <p>Reſerving withall for Us, Our Brethren, neere Kindred, and all
thoſe that have any in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt <pb n="21" facs="tcp:25234:13"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 13 -->in
it, to uſe all ſuch law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full and conducible meanes, actions, defences and
remedies, as are allowed in ſuch caſes, by Divine and humane lawes, to all,
that are thus oppreſſed, and ſuffer ſuch wrongs and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>juries, with
this expreſſe de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claration and Proteſtation, that whereas We Ourſelves,
and others for Vs have hitherto tryed and ſought, as much as was
poſſible, to come by faire <pb n="22" facs="tcp:25234:14"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->meanes
to the quiet repoſſeſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of what belongeth unto Vs, by Nature, and
Lawes Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine and humane, upon honeſt and tolerable conditions, We deſire
to be cleare and blame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſſe before Almighty God, the whole world, and all
poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity, of whatſoever may befall any one in the proſecution and
maintaining of Our juſt and lawfull cauſe, for the ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining of Our
reſtitution.</p>
            <pb n="23" facs="tcp:25234:14"/>
            <!-- PDF PAGE 14 -->
            <p>We doe likewiſe in the end profeſſe and proteſt before
God, who knoweth the hearts of man, that VVe doe not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend by this our forced
lawfull Proteſtation, to derogate any thing from the Highneſſe and
preheminency of his Imperiall Majeſty, whom We are wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and ready to
honour and revere with moſt humble and conſtant devotion, Or to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh
and offend the Rights, <pb n="24" facs="tcp:25234:15"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->Honours,
and Iuriſdictions of any State ſoever, having no other intent and ſcope,
but more and more by theſe law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full meanes to maintaine, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme, and
publikely to mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt Our innocency, juſt cauſe, unqueſtionable Right,
Here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditary Dignities, and lawfull poſſeſsions, leaſt by Our ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence
and forbearance of this neceſſary and juſt Proteſtati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, they ſhould
be neglected, <pb n="25" facs="tcp:25234:15"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 15 -->endangered, or
prejudiced,</p>
            <p>And to the end, that this Our Proteſtation, drawne in the
preſence of a Notary and witneſſes, might come to the publike knowledge
and view of the world, and all frivolous exceptions and pretences of ignorance
be cut off from thoſe whom it may concerne, We have cauſed it publikely to
be ſet forth and printed, and have <pb n="26" facs="tcp:25234:16"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->already
ſent ſome authenticke copies of it to his Imperiall Majeſty, and the
Princes E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lectours, under Our owne hand and Seale.</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <hi>Given at Hampton-court</hi> 
                  <date>
                     <hi>the 27. of January, anno</hi> 1637.</date>
               </dateline> 
               <pb facs="tcp:25234:16"/>
               <!-- PDF PAGE 16 -->
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
